<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-09-23T05:24:32+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Embracing Diversity - A Progressive Outlook on Gender in the Tech Field</title><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/diversity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embracing Diversity - A Progressive Outlook on Gender in the Tech Field"/><published>2023-08-04T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-04T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/diversity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/diversity/"><![CDATA[<p>Hey everyone, today I want to delve into a crucial topic that has been at the forefront of conversations within the tech industry – gender diversity. The world of technology has seen remarkable advancements, yet it remains predominantly male-dominated. In this post, I’d like to share my opinion on why embracing gender diversity is essential for the tech field’s continued growth and success.</p> <p>First and foremost, gender diversity brings about a wide range of perspectives, ideas, and experiences. By having a balanced workforce that includes people of all genders, we foster creativity and innovation. Different backgrounds and viewpoints challenge the status quo, leading to more robust solutions and products that cater to a diverse global audience.</p> <p>Moreover, studies have shown that diverse teams have higher collective intelligence and outperform homogeneous groups. When everyone has an equal chance to participate and contribute, team dynamics improve, and collaboration becomes more effective. As a result, companies with diverse teams are more likely to attract top talent and remain competitive in an ever-evolving tech landscape.</p> <p>Addressing the gender gap in tech is not only a moral imperative but also an economic one. According to research, gender-diverse companies tend to perform better financially. Companies that embrace gender diversity report higher revenues and better returns on investment. By encouraging and empowering more women to enter the tech industry, we can unlock a vast pool of untapped talent that can drive economic growth and innovation.</p> <p>In conclusion, embracing gender diversity in the tech field is not just a social goal; it is an essential strategic move. By promoting an inclusive work environment, we can foster innovation, increase productivity, and drive economic growth.</p> <p>What is your opinion on gender diversity in tech?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hey everyone, today I want to delve into a crucial topic that has been at the forefront of conversations within the tech industry – gender diversity. The world of technology has seen remarkable advancements, yet it remains predominantly male-dominated. In this post, I’d like to share my opinion on why embracing gender diversity is essential for the tech field’s continued growth and success.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Shapash - library to make ML interpretable and understandable</title><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/shapash/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shapash - library to make ML interpretable and understandable"/><published>2023-07-01T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-01T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/shapash</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/shapash/"><![CDATA[<p>I found this today, and I think this is very fun to try. <a href="https://github.com/MAIF/shapash">Shapash</a> is a Python library designed to enhance the interpretability and comprehensibility of machine learning models for all users. Its primary objective is to provide various visualizations that present explicit labels, ensuring ease of understanding for everyone.</p> <p>For Data Scientists, Shapash simplifies the comprehension of models and facilitates result-sharing. It enables them to easily interpret the decisions made by models through a summary of the most influential criteria.</p> <p>Moreover, Shapash plays a significant role in data science auditing by offering informative insights about any model and data in a comprehensive report.</p> <p>Additionally, Shapash allows the generation of user-friendly web applications that aid in analyzing complex models. This accessibility extends to both Data Scientists and individuals with non-technical backgrounds, such as field experts.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/4.gif-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/4.gif-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/4.gif-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/4.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="resources"/><category term="git"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I found this today, and I think this is very fun to try. Shapash is a Python library designed to enhance the interpretability and comprehensibility of machine learning models for all users. Its primary objective is to provide various visualizations that present explicit labels, ensuring ease of understanding for everyone.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">STAR Format for Behavioral Interviews</title><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/STAR/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="STAR Format for Behavioral Interviews"/><published>2023-06-24T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-24T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/STAR</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/STAR/"><![CDATA[<p>Are you preparing for an upcoming job interview (I think it’s the time of the year for this preparation lol)?</p> <p>The behavioral interview is where employers ask questions about past experiences and how you handled specific situations. These questions aim to assess your skills, behavior, and problem-solving abilities. One effective technique for acing it is using the STAR format</p> <ul> <li><strong>Situation</strong> Describe the situation or context you faced. Provide enough background information to give the interviewer a good understanding of the scenario you are about to discuss. Remember to keep the focus on yourself and your role in the situation.</li> <li><strong>Task</strong> Outline the specific task or challenge you needed to address. What goal were you working towards? What obstacles or objectives did you need to overcome?</li> <li><strong>Action</strong> This is the heart of your response. Describe the actions you took to address the situation and accomplish the task. Explain the steps you followed, highlighting your skills, decision-making abilities, and leadership qualities. You can use JDs to tailor this to bold that you’re a perfect candidate. Be specific and emphasize the actions you personally undertook to highlight your individual contribution.</li> <li><strong>Result</strong> What were the results of your efforts? Focus on quantifiable achievements, such as increased productivity, cost savings, or positive feedback received. If possible, mention any recognition or accolades you received for your work.</li> </ul> <p>The STAR format can be expanded to STARI, with the <strong>I</strong> representing <strong>Improvement</strong>. <strong>Improvement</strong> Discuss the improvements you identified or the lessons you learned from the experience. Reflect on the challenges you faced and explain how you grew both personally and professionally. Discuss any adjustments you would make if faced with a similar situation in the future, demonstrating your ability to learn from your experiences.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/1-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/1-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/1-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>By using the STAR(I) format, you provide a structured and comprehensive response that showcases your abilities and accomplishments. Here are a few additional tips to keep in mind when using this format:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Prepare examples:</strong> Anticipate potential behavioral questions and prepare examples in advance. You can search for popular behavior questions and prepare based on these. Use Chat GPT to make it better, I think GPT can be very helpful on this. After any interview, if there are any questions that you haven’t prepared, add them to your list, and prepare them as new examples.</li> <li><strong>Focus on different competencies:</strong> Behavioral questions can cover a wide range of competencies, such as problem-solving, leadership, teamwork, adaptability, and communication. Ensure you have examples that showcase different competencies to address a variety of questions.</li> <li><strong>Practice storytelling:</strong> Craft your responses as engaging stories. Use descriptive language (Chat GPT can help with this 😉) to paint a vivid picture of the situation, and make sure to convey your thought process and emotions throughout the narrative. Engaging storytelling can leave a lasting impression on the interviewer.</li> <li><strong>Quantify when possible:</strong> Whenever feasible, include quantifiable results in your responses. Numbers and metrics provide concrete evidence of your impact and make your accomplishments more compelling.</li> </ol> <p>Remember, practice makes perfect. Rehearse your STAR(I) format responses, focusing on clarity, conciseness, and impact. Use mock interviews or ask a friend to play the role of the interviewer, providing feedback on your delivery and content.</p> <p>By mastering the STAR format, you’ll be well-equipped to handle behavioral interviews.</p> <p>Good luck!!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general"/><category term="career"/><category term="general"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Are you preparing for an upcoming job interview (I think it’s the time of the year for this preparation lol)?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Build Portfolio Projects</title><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/portfolio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Build Portfolio Projects"/><published>2023-06-21T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/portfolio</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/portfolio/"><![CDATA[<p>Today I want to talk about building an impressive portfolio since it is essential for showcasing your skills and experience. So, let’s dive into the key takeaways for creating an outstanding portfolio project!</p> <ol> <li><strong>Genuine Interest, Simplicity, and Impact</strong>: Choose a project that aligns with your passion and curiosity. When you are genuinely interested in the subject matter, your enthusiasm will shine through in your work. And during your interview.</li> <li><strong>Experience Gap</strong>: Very important if you lack internships or relevant work experience, portfolio projects become a crucial way to bridge this gap. They demonstrate your practical skills and ability to apply data science techniques to solve problems. Hence, focus on the skills of the role you aim for, for example, as I aim for DS, I did several <em>ML, visualization, and exploratory</em> projects because these keywords appear a lot in DS job descriptions.</li> <li><strong>Showcasing Impact and Results</strong>: Did your project lead to a measurable improvement in a company’s operations? Did it catch the interest of your community or solve a pressing problem? Highlight these outcomes to showcase the value of your work. Aim to make a quantifiable impact (so that you have a <em>number</em> to write in your resume) and show that the impact of your project is crucial.</li> <li><strong>Clear Communication and Documentation</strong>: Pay attention to how you communicate your process, methodology, and results so that anyone can understand them. Ensure that your project documentation is clear, concise, and well-organized. Provide an overview of the problem, the data, and the techniques/algorithms. Emphasizing clear communication and documentation helps show your ability to convey complex ideas. This skill is highly valued, too.</li> </ol> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Happy creating!</p> <hr/> <p><em>More about <strong>metrics</strong>: One way to elevate your portfolio project is by demonstrating how it has helped others or delivered tangible benefits, and using metrics is a powerful way to showcase the impact of your work. Metrics provide quantifiable evidence of the results and emphasize the value of your project, especially when presenting to people who may not have a deep understanding of code or technical details. Hiring managers or decision-makers who may not be well-versed in coding or technical intricacies are the ones who scan your resume first; hence, numbers help them skim faster and quantifiable results help them quickly grasp the magnitude of your work.</em></p> <p><em>Specific metrics, such as revenue increase, cost savings, or user engagement, are very very helpful, but most of the time we cannot have these. So, if your project involves machine learning or predictive modeling, you can showcase performance metrics like F1 score or accuracy score. Then, you can effectively demonstrate the effectiveness and accuracy of your models, further emphasizing the value they bring.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general"/><category term="education"/><category term="career"/><category term="project"/><category term="general"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today I want to talk about building an impressive portfolio since it is essential for showcasing your skills and experience. So, let’s dive into the key takeaways for creating an outstanding portfolio project!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Challenges in Job Hunt</title><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/job-hunt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Challenges in Job Hunt"/><published>2023-06-17T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-17T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/job-hunt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/job-hunt/"><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to share a personal thought with you all about my journey in applying for DS/DA/DE jobs. I think it’s important for us to be open and honest about the challenges we face, so that we can support each other and realize that we’re not alone in this process.</p> <ol> <li><strong>Require MS/PhD</strong>: When I first started applying for data science positions, I quickly realized that many of the open roles required a master’s or PhD degree. As someone who didn’t have those qualifications yet, it felt intimidating. I knew that competition would be fierce, and I was worried about how I would stand out among candidates with more experience and higher degrees.</li> <li><strong>Ghosted by companies</strong>: I submitted countless applications (probably 1000+) and rarely hear back from the companies I applied to. It was disheartening and made me doubt my abilities. I began questioning if there were weaknesses in my resume that I hadn’t identified, causing recruiters to overlook me. But it’s important to remember that this is a common experience for many job seekers, and it doesn’t necessarily reflect our skills or potential.</li> <li><strong>Tech interviews</strong>: I had no idea what companies were looking for or what to expect, it’s not just grinding LeetCode, since the topics covered in these interviews were so vast and varied: data scientist, data analyst, data engineer, or machine learning engineer. And many times, you may come across a DS role that asks you questions more aligned with DE.</li> </ol> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/8-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/8-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/8-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/8.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>I wanted to share this story with you all to let you know that the difficulties we face in the job application process are normal. It’s easy to get discouraged, but remember that everyone goes through similar challenges. It’s important to support and encourage one another.</p> <p>I really hope that we can hear more tips or success stories from people in this server. But keep in mind this: Keep working on your skills, keep improving your resume, keep applying, and keep pushing forward.</p> <p>Happy weekend!!!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general"/><category term="career"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I wanted to share a personal thought with you all about my journey in applying for DS/DA/DE jobs. I think it’s important for us to be open and honest about the challenges we face, so that we can support each other and realize that we’re not alone in this process.]]></summary></entry></feed>