<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-09-23T05:50:53+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Embracing Diversity - A Progressive Outlook on Gender in the Tech Field</title><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/diversity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embracing Diversity - A Progressive Outlook on Gender in the Tech Field"/><published>2023-08-04T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-04T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/diversity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/diversity/"><![CDATA[<p>Hey everyone, today I want to delve into a crucial topic that has been at the forefront of conversations within the tech industry – gender diversity. The world of technology has seen remarkable advancements, yet it remains predominantly male-dominated. In this post, I’d like to share my opinion on why embracing gender diversity is essential for the tech field’s continued growth and success.</p> <p>First and foremost, gender diversity brings about a wide range of perspectives, ideas, and experiences. By having a balanced workforce that includes people of all genders, we foster creativity and innovation. Different backgrounds and viewpoints challenge the status quo, leading to more robust solutions and products that cater to a diverse global audience.</p> <p>Moreover, studies have shown that diverse teams have higher collective intelligence and outperform homogeneous groups. When everyone has an equal chance to participate and contribute, team dynamics improve, and collaboration becomes more effective. As a result, companies with diverse teams are more likely to attract top talent and remain competitive in an ever-evolving tech landscape.</p> <p>Addressing the gender gap in tech is not only a moral imperative but also an economic one. According to research, gender-diverse companies tend to perform better financially. Companies that embrace gender diversity report higher revenues and better returns on investment. By encouraging and empowering more women to enter the tech industry, we can unlock a vast pool of untapped talent that can drive economic growth and innovation.</p> <p>In conclusion, embracing gender diversity in the tech field is not just a social goal; it is an essential strategic move. By promoting an inclusive work environment, we can foster innovation, increase productivity, and drive economic growth.</p> <p>What is your opinion on gender diversity in tech?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hey everyone, today I want to delve into a crucial topic that has been at the forefront of conversations within the tech industry – gender diversity. The world of technology has seen remarkable advancements, yet it remains predominantly male-dominated. In this post, I’d like to share my opinion on why embracing gender diversity is essential for the tech field’s continued growth and success.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Preparing for Success - Navigating Your Data Science Interview with Confidence</title><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/interview-prep/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Preparing for Success - Navigating Your Data Science Interview with Confidence"/><published>2023-07-07T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-07T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/interview-prep</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/interview-prep/"><![CDATA[<p>I am incredibly grateful to have recently secured a co-op position as a data scientist with Oracle. Throughout my own experiences and insights gained during the interview and resume preparation process, I believe I can offer valuable advice to those who are currently in Round B or planning to apply for future internships or co-ops. However, I want to emphasize that everyone’s path is unique, and success ultimately comes from a combination of hard work, preparation, and a touch of luck. With that in mind, let’s dive into some tips that I think can maximize your chances of success (I’ll skip general tips)!</p> <h2 id="1-resume-preparation">1. <strong>Resume preparation</strong>:</h2> <ol> <li>While taking the COOP 101 class is essential, I’ve found that it’s crucial to go beyond what is covered in the course. Although it provides a solid foundation, you should strive to showcase your skills and experiences in a more detailed and tangible way to make your resume more competitive and stand out. Instead of simply listing relevant coursework, consider highlighting the skills you acquired through personal projects and work experiences. By providing specific examples, you can better demonstrate your abilities and qualifications to potential employers. For instance, rather than just mentioning that you took the INFO 212 Data Science Programming course, include a data science project you worked on during the class and outline the techniques/skills you utilized. Remember, recruiters and hiring managers may not be familiar with specific course names.</li> <li>Another tip is to customize your resume based on the specific role you are applying for. While it’s always beneficial to have multiple resumes tailored to different roles, personally, I found that customizing my resume based on the job description made a significant difference. Take the time to thoroughly review the job description, especially those that truly interest you, and compare it to your resume. Identify any keywords or skills mentioned in the description that you possess but haven’t included in your resume. Consider learning more about other relevant topics to enhance your suitability for the role. This proactive approach can make you stand out as a candidate genuinely interested in the position and help you learn new things outside of your academic coursework. In my experience, whenever I came across a job description aligned with my interests and aspirations, I updated my resume almost every day throughout the internship application process.</li> <li>Lastly, don’t underestimate the power of seeking advice and feedback from professionals in the field. Reach out to individuals who hold the job title you aspire to or who work at companies you admire. They possess valuable insights into their respective roles and companies. However, remember to use your own judgment and instincts when evaluating their advice, as you know yourself and your goals best.</li> </ol> <p>I still have plenty more tips that I’d love to share, but for now, let’s move on to interview preparation.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/6-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/6-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/6-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/6.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="2-interview-preparation">2. <strong>Interview Preparation</strong>:</h2> <ol> <li>When it comes to interview preparation, thoroughly study the job description and research the interviewers and the team you may potentially join. This will help you tailor your preparation to their specific needs and work style. Harnessing the power of ChatGPT can also streamline your interview preparation process. Utilize the model to analyze job descriptions, company information, and your own experiences. Personally, I’ve found reading job descriptions or researching about the team or company to be a bit tedious and easy to forget. This is where ChatGPT comes in. Prior to each interview, I would input information about myself, my experiences, the job description, and any relevant details about the job that I found helpful. I would then ask ChatGPT questions like “Why do you think you are suitable for the job?” or “Why do you want to work for the company?” or “What makes you a good candidate?”. By doing this, I received customized responses that served as a foundation for my interview preparation. Researching the team and individuals involved allows us to narrow down our focus and better prepare for the specific requirements of the role. Additionally, ChatGPT helped me generate thoughtful follow-up questions, showcasing my dedication and genuine interest in the role.</li> <li>Next, let’s discuss the importance of follow-up questions. In my experience, they play a crucial role since they demonstrate your dedication and the research you conducted on the team and company prior to and during the interview. I even received feedback from an interviewer who mentioned that the most impressive part of my interview was my follow-up question, as it showed my interest in a particular aspect where the team needed additional support (PS: I know that luck played a role in this, haha).</li> </ol> <h2 id="3-my-own-interview-experience">3. <strong>My Own Interview Experience</strong>:</h2> <p>For this co-op interview preparation, I searched the name of my interviewer to see what they did in the past. My approach was to sell myself and showcase as many aspects of myself as possible. What I learned is that the team uses a lot of ML and AI, utilizing SQL for data preparation, and heavily focusing on optimizing these models. As a result, I dedicated my time to learning ML and AI, revising different ML models for classification and regression, understanding metrics like F1 score and accuracy, and exploring techniques for NLP and dataset dimensionality. I also refreshed my knowledge of SQL, particularly focusing on techniques and popular queries for data preparation. During my interview, whenever I talked about my past experience, I made sure to highlight how I optimized or planned to optimize. I also emphasized my knowledge in ML and AI, specifically in the areas of NLP and healthcare data, as I discovered that the team had projects related to those domains. I actively steered the conversation towards health and NLP (I didn’t have experience in business), allowing them to ask me more questions in those areas. By leading the interview in a way that showcased my preparedness and skills, I was able to present myself in the best light possible. Of course, luck also played a part, as the projects they were working on aligned with the field I had put a lot of effort into and had sufficient experience in.</p> <p>Overall, my advice here is that with enough and correct preparation, you can lead the interview and exert some control over it. This can boost your confidence and allow you to showcase yourself to the fullest.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-sci"/><category term="experience"/><category term="career"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I am incredibly grateful to have recently secured a co-op position as a data scientist with Oracle. Throughout my own experiences and insights gained during the interview and resume preparation process, I believe I can offer valuable advice to those who are currently in Round B or planning to apply for future internships or co-ops. However, I want to emphasize that everyone’s path is unique, and success ultimately comes from a combination of hard work, preparation, and a touch of luck. With that in mind, let’s dive into some tips that I think can maximize your chances of success (I’ll skip general tips)!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Shapash - library to make ML interpretable and understandable</title><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/shapash/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shapash - library to make ML interpretable and understandable"/><published>2023-07-01T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-01T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/shapash</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/shapash/"><![CDATA[<p>I found this today, and I think this is very fun to try. <a href="https://github.com/MAIF/shapash">Shapash</a> is a Python library designed to enhance the interpretability and comprehensibility of machine learning models for all users. Its primary objective is to provide various visualizations that present explicit labels, ensuring ease of understanding for everyone.</p> <p>For Data Scientists, Shapash simplifies the comprehension of models and facilitates result-sharing. It enables them to easily interpret the decisions made by models through a summary of the most influential criteria.</p> <p>Moreover, Shapash plays a significant role in data science auditing by offering informative insights about any model and data in a comprehensive report.</p> <p>Additionally, Shapash allows the generation of user-friendly web applications that aid in analyzing complex models. This accessibility extends to both Data Scientists and individuals with non-technical backgrounds, such as field experts.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/4.gif-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/4.gif-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/4.gif-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/4.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="resources"/><category term="git"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I found this today, and I think this is very fun to try. Shapash is a Python library designed to enhance the interpretability and comprehensibility of machine learning models for all users. Its primary objective is to provide various visualizations that present explicit labels, ensuring ease of understanding for everyone.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">STAR Format for Behavioral Interviews</title><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/STAR/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="STAR Format for Behavioral Interviews"/><published>2023-06-24T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-24T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/STAR</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/STAR/"><![CDATA[<p>Are you preparing for an upcoming job interview (I think it’s the time of the year for this preparation lol)?</p> <p>The behavioral interview is where employers ask questions about past experiences and how you handled specific situations. These questions aim to assess your skills, behavior, and problem-solving abilities. One effective technique for acing it is using the STAR format</p> <ul> <li><strong>Situation</strong> Describe the situation or context you faced. Provide enough background information to give the interviewer a good understanding of the scenario you are about to discuss. Remember to keep the focus on yourself and your role in the situation.</li> <li><strong>Task</strong> Outline the specific task or challenge you needed to address. What goal were you working towards? What obstacles or objectives did you need to overcome?</li> <li><strong>Action</strong> This is the heart of your response. Describe the actions you took to address the situation and accomplish the task. Explain the steps you followed, highlighting your skills, decision-making abilities, and leadership qualities. You can use JDs to tailor this to bold that you’re a perfect candidate. Be specific and emphasize the actions you personally undertook to highlight your individual contribution.</li> <li><strong>Result</strong> What were the results of your efforts? Focus on quantifiable achievements, such as increased productivity, cost savings, or positive feedback received. If possible, mention any recognition or accolades you received for your work.</li> </ul> <p>The STAR format can be expanded to STARI, with the <strong>I</strong> representing <strong>Improvement</strong>. <strong>Improvement</strong> Discuss the improvements you identified or the lessons you learned from the experience. Reflect on the challenges you faced and explain how you grew both personally and professionally. Discuss any adjustments you would make if faced with a similar situation in the future, demonstrating your ability to learn from your experiences.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/1-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/1-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/1-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>By using the STAR(I) format, you provide a structured and comprehensive response that showcases your abilities and accomplishments. Here are a few additional tips to keep in mind when using this format:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Prepare examples:</strong> Anticipate potential behavioral questions and prepare examples in advance. You can search for popular behavior questions and prepare based on these. Use Chat GPT to make it better, I think GPT can be very helpful on this. After any interview, if there are any questions that you haven’t prepared, add them to your list, and prepare them as new examples.</li> <li><strong>Focus on different competencies:</strong> Behavioral questions can cover a wide range of competencies, such as problem-solving, leadership, teamwork, adaptability, and communication. Ensure you have examples that showcase different competencies to address a variety of questions.</li> <li><strong>Practice storytelling:</strong> Craft your responses as engaging stories. Use descriptive language (Chat GPT can help with this 😉) to paint a vivid picture of the situation, and make sure to convey your thought process and emotions throughout the narrative. Engaging storytelling can leave a lasting impression on the interviewer.</li> <li><strong>Quantify when possible:</strong> Whenever feasible, include quantifiable results in your responses. Numbers and metrics provide concrete evidence of your impact and make your accomplishments more compelling.</li> </ol> <p>Remember, practice makes perfect. Rehearse your STAR(I) format responses, focusing on clarity, conciseness, and impact. Use mock interviews or ask a friend to play the role of the interviewer, providing feedback on your delivery and content.</p> <p>By mastering the STAR format, you’ll be well-equipped to handle behavioral interviews.</p> <p>Good luck!!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general"/><category term="career"/><category term="general"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Are you preparing for an upcoming job interview (I think it’s the time of the year for this preparation lol)?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring the Importance of Different Distance Metrics in Machine Learning</title><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/distance-ml/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring the Importance of Different Distance Metrics in Machine Learning"/><published>2023-06-23T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-23T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/distance-ml</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/distance-ml/"><![CDATA[<p>Today I learned 😂😂 I found this post on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/mehdihamedi_distances-machinelearning-distances-activity-7077582759099027457-Q4eh/">LinkedIn</a> and I think this is helpful. In numerous real-world scenarios, ML algorithms are utilized for tasks like image classification, image recognition, and information retrieval based on image content. Selecting an appropriate distance metric plays a crucial role in these applications as it enables algorithms to identify similarities between different image contents. So, I believe that the better you understand the foundation of the ML models you use, the better you use them.</p> <p><strong>What?</strong> According to a basic mathematical definition (source: Wikipedia), a distance metric utilizes a distance function to establish a measurement of the relationship between individual elements within a dataset.</p> <p>For me, during my classes, I notice that professors frequently mentioned distance metrics, but I often overlooked their significance as I didn’t consider them particularly helpful.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/5-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/5-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/5-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/5.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p><strong>Why important?</strong></p> <ul> <li>Several supervised and unsupervised learning algorithms rely on distances, including k-means clustering and k-nearest neighbors.</li> <li>Among the commonly used distance metrics, Euclidean distance is the most popular. However, there are other distance metrics like Manhattan distance, Chebyshev distance, and Minkowski distance, each with their own advantages and disadvantages.</li> <li>For instance, the Manhattan distance is useful when the dimensions in the data have different units of measurement, while the Chebyshev distance is suitable for applications where the maximum difference between two dimensions is more important. Please read the post for more details on other examples.</li> <li>Understanding the strengths and weaknesses of each distance metric is crucial in selecting the appropriate one for a specific problem. By choosing the right distance metric, we can enhance the accuracy and efficiency of our ML models.</li> </ul> <hr/> <p>I think an example will make this easier to understand, because I need an example to understand this.</p> <p>Again, distance metrics’ primary purpose is to measure the similarity between data points, which significantly impacts the performance of machine learning models, be it for classification tasks or clustering.</p> <p>Imagine you are working on creating clusters using algorithms like K-Means Clustering or the k-nearest neighbor algorithm (cliche 🤭), which leverages nearest neighbors for solving classification or regression problems. How would you determine the similarity between different observations? How can we establish that the two points are similar? The answer lies in assessing the similarity of their features. When these points are plotted, their closeness or distance from each other becomes apparent.</p> <p>Therefore, we calculate the distance between data points and utilize it to define their similarity. Now, the question arises: How do we compute this distance, and what are the various distance metrics employed in machine learning? Do these metrics differ based on the type of learning problem? Do we apply any specific theorems for this purpose? These are all important queries that highlight the significance of understanding the distance metrics used in machine learning.</p> <p>Some popular distances you may have heard of before are: <strong>Euclidean</strong>, <strong>Manhattan</strong>, <strong>Minkowski</strong>, or <strong>Hamming</strong> distances. You can start looking at these distances first.</p> <p>Copied from <a href="https://www.datarlabs.com/post/measuring-the-unmeasurable-the-power-of-distance-metrics-in-data-science">DataR Labs</a></p> <p><strong>Types of commonly used distance metrics</strong> There are many types of distance metrics used in data science, each with its own strengths and weaknesses. Some of the most commonly used distance metrics include:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Euclidean distance</strong>: This is the straight-line distance between two points in a multi-dimensional space. It is the most commonly used distance metric and is suitable for continuous variables.</li> <li><strong>Manhattan distance</strong>: Also known as taxicab distance, it measures the distance between two points by adding the absolute differences of their coordinates. It is useful for discrete variables.</li> <li><strong>Minkowski distance</strong>: This is a generalized distance metric that includes Euclidean and Manhattan distance as special cases. It is defined as the pth root of the sum of the pth power of the absolute differences between coordinates.</li> <li><strong>Cosine similarity</strong>: This metric measures the cosine of the angle between two vectors. It is used for text data and other sparse data where the magnitude of the vector is less important than the direction.</li> <li><strong>Chebyshev distance</strong>: Chebyshev distance, also known as chessboard distance or L∞ distance, is a metric used to measure the distance between two points in a grid system where movement is restricted to horizontal, vertical, and diagonal directions.</li> <li><strong>Hamming distance</strong>: This is a metric used for comparing two strings of equal length. It measures the number of positions at which the corresponding symbols are different.</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-sci"/><category term="ml"/><category term="math"/><category term="technology"/><category term="modeling"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today I learned 😂😂 I found this post on LinkedIn and I think this is helpful. In numerous real-world scenarios, ML algorithms are utilized for tasks like image classification, image recognition, and information retrieval based on image content. Selecting an appropriate distance metric plays a crucial role in these applications as it enables algorithms to identify similarities between different image contents. So, I believe that the better you understand the foundation of the ML models you use, the better you use them.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Build Portfolio Projects</title><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/portfolio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Build Portfolio Projects"/><published>2023-06-21T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/portfolio</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/portfolio/"><![CDATA[<p>Today I want to talk about building an impressive portfolio since it is essential for showcasing your skills and experience. So, let’s dive into the key takeaways for creating an outstanding portfolio project!</p> <ol> <li><strong>Genuine Interest, Simplicity, and Impact</strong>: Choose a project that aligns with your passion and curiosity. When you are genuinely interested in the subject matter, your enthusiasm will shine through in your work. And during your interview.</li> <li><strong>Experience Gap</strong>: Very important if you lack internships or relevant work experience, portfolio projects become a crucial way to bridge this gap. They demonstrate your practical skills and ability to apply data science techniques to solve problems. Hence, focus on the skills of the role you aim for, for example, as I aim for DS, I did several <em>ML, visualization, and exploratory</em> projects because these keywords appear a lot in DS job descriptions.</li> <li><strong>Showcasing Impact and Results</strong>: Did your project lead to a measurable improvement in a company’s operations? Did it catch the interest of your community or solve a pressing problem? Highlight these outcomes to showcase the value of your work. Aim to make a quantifiable impact (so that you have a <em>number</em> to write in your resume) and show that the impact of your project is crucial.</li> <li><strong>Clear Communication and Documentation</strong>: Pay attention to how you communicate your process, methodology, and results so that anyone can understand them. Ensure that your project documentation is clear, concise, and well-organized. Provide an overview of the problem, the data, and the techniques/algorithms. Emphasizing clear communication and documentation helps show your ability to convey complex ideas. This skill is highly valued, too.</li> </ol> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Happy creating!</p> <hr/> <p><em>More about <strong>metrics</strong>: One way to elevate your portfolio project is by demonstrating how it has helped others or delivered tangible benefits, and using metrics is a powerful way to showcase the impact of your work. Metrics provide quantifiable evidence of the results and emphasize the value of your project, especially when presenting to people who may not have a deep understanding of code or technical details. Hiring managers or decision-makers who may not be well-versed in coding or technical intricacies are the ones who scan your resume first; hence, numbers help them skim faster and quantifiable results help them quickly grasp the magnitude of your work.</em></p> <p><em>Specific metrics, such as revenue increase, cost savings, or user engagement, are very very helpful, but most of the time we cannot have these. So, if your project involves machine learning or predictive modeling, you can showcase performance metrics like F1 score or accuracy score. Then, you can effectively demonstrate the effectiveness and accuracy of your models, further emphasizing the value they bring.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general"/><category term="education"/><category term="career"/><category term="project"/><category term="general"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today I want to talk about building an impressive portfolio since it is essential for showcasing your skills and experience. So, let’s dive into the key takeaways for creating an outstanding portfolio project!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building a Resume with No Experience</title><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/resume-build/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building a Resume with No Experience"/><published>2023-06-19T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-19T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/resume-build</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/resume-build/"><![CDATA[<p>It can be discouraging to see job postings that require experience when you’re just starting, but, there are still several things you can do to enhance your resume and stand out to potential employers. This is something I did before I got my first interview invitation.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/7-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/7-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/7-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/7.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <ol> <li><strong>Leverage your education</strong>: Since we don’t have any professional experience, your education will be a valuable asset. Highlight relevant coursework, projects, and academic achievements, and be specific about the techniques, tools, and technologies you’ve learned or worked.</li> <li><strong>Part-time jobs</strong>: Seek out positions where you can apply your skills and gain practical knowledge. For me, it is becoming Course or Research Assisstant. This helps show off soft skills and your enthusiasm for the field.</li> <li><strong>Personal projects and open-source contributions</strong>: Take the initiative to work on personal projects or contribute to open-source projects (<em>Kaggle</em>). Building your own data analysis or machine learning projects can showcase your abilities and demonstrate your passion for the subject. These projects not only provide practical experience but also demonstrate your ability to take initiative and work independently. Most of the time, interviewers ask me questions related to my personal projects and some even go to my GitHub and asked about things I didn’t even show in my resume yet.</li> <li><strong>Volunteer work and extracurricular activities</strong>: Yeah, it’s just helpful. And fun 😗</li> </ol> <p>Remember, building a strong resume takes time and effort. Don’t get discouraged if you face rejections. Keep refining your skills, seeking opportunities to gain practical experience, and showcasing your passion for the field.</p> <p>Best of luck!</p> <hr/> <p>I want to share more about <strong>research assistant</strong> and shed light on the incredible opportunities it offers for resume building. Many students often overlook the advantages of being a research assistant, assuming it is solely for those pursuing research careers. However, I believe that a research assistantship can be an excellent starting point for any job seeker, regardless of their background or level of experience.</p> <p>I have been fortunate enough to work with two professors who have provided me with invaluable experiences and learning opportunities (and now, for me, it’s more than just that). One professor allowed me to collaborate on several ML projects, enabling me to gain practical skills and knowledge in the field. The other professor exposed me to the world of research, teaching me valuable insights and methodologies through her lab. The work I undertook with both professors greatly impressed some of my interviewers, as they recognized the significance and ask me several things about the projects I worked on.</p> <p>Also, what makes research assistantships particularly valuable is that they don’t require extensive prerequisites. In my case, I became a research assistant after studying DS for just four months.</p> <p>If you have any questions related to being a research assistant or would like to know more about my experiences, please feel free to ask. I highly recommend considering research assistantships as an excellent stepping stone in your career journey.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-sci"/><category term="experience"/><category term="career"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It can be discouraging to see job postings that require experience when you’re just starting, but, there are still several things you can do to enhance your resume and stand out to potential employers. This is something I did before I got my first interview invitation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Challenges in Job Hunt</title><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/job-hunt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Challenges in Job Hunt"/><published>2023-06-17T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-17T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/job-hunt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/job-hunt/"><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to share a personal thought with you all about my journey in applying for DS/DA/DE jobs. I think it’s important for us to be open and honest about the challenges we face, so that we can support each other and realize that we’re not alone in this process.</p> <ol> <li><strong>Require MS/PhD</strong>: When I first started applying for data science positions, I quickly realized that many of the open roles required a master’s or PhD degree. As someone who didn’t have those qualifications yet, it felt intimidating. I knew that competition would be fierce, and I was worried about how I would stand out among candidates with more experience and higher degrees.</li> <li><strong>Ghosted by companies</strong>: I submitted countless applications (probably 1000+) and rarely hear back from the companies I applied to. It was disheartening and made me doubt my abilities. I began questioning if there were weaknesses in my resume that I hadn’t identified, causing recruiters to overlook me. But it’s important to remember that this is a common experience for many job seekers, and it doesn’t necessarily reflect our skills or potential.</li> <li><strong>Tech interviews</strong>: I had no idea what companies were looking for or what to expect, it’s not just grinding LeetCode, since the topics covered in these interviews were so vast and varied: data scientist, data analyst, data engineer, or machine learning engineer. And many times, you may come across a DS role that asks you questions more aligned with DE.</li> </ol> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/8-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/8-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/8-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/8.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>I wanted to share this story with you all to let you know that the difficulties we face in the job application process are normal. It’s easy to get discouraged, but remember that everyone goes through similar challenges. It’s important to support and encourage one another.</p> <p>I really hope that we can hear more tips or success stories from people in this server. But keep in mind this: Keep working on your skills, keep improving your resume, keep applying, and keep pushing forward.</p> <p>Happy weekend!!!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general"/><category term="career"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I wanted to share a personal thought with you all about my journey in applying for DS/DA/DE jobs. I think it’s important for us to be open and honest about the challenges we face, so that we can support each other and realize that we’re not alone in this process.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Common Myths and Misconceptions in Data Science - Let’s Debunk Them!</title><link href="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/data-sci-math/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Common Myths and Misconceptions in Data Science - Let’s Debunk Them!"/><published>2023-06-15T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-15T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/data-sci-math</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://npl0204.github.io/blog/2023/data-sci-math/"><![CDATA[<p>Hey everyone!</p> <p>Data science (<em>DSCI</em>) is an incredibly exciting and rapidly growing field. However, it’s not without its fair share of myths and misconceptions that can confuse and set unrealistic expectations for aspiring or practicing data scientists. Let’s take a moment to debunk some of the most common misconceptions that we often encounter.</p> <p><strong>Myth 1: DSCI is solely about coding</strong> While coding is undoubtedly vital in DSCI, it’s not the be-all and end-all of the field. DSCI encompasses much more than just coding. It involves understanding the domain, the problem, and the data, and employing appropriate methods and tools to extract insights and devise solutions. Soft skills like problem-solving, critical thinking, attention to detail, and creativity are equally important. Furthermore, effective communication skills are crucial for conveying complex concepts to non-technical stakeholders.</p> <p><strong>Myth 2: DSCI is objective and unbiased</strong> While DSCI aims for objectivity, it’s important to acknowledge that it’s not completely immune to human biases and errors. Biases can creep into data collection, analysis, and interpretation due to cognitive or technical factors. Data scientists must approach their work with a critical mindset and be aware of the ethical implications of their decisions.</p> <p><strong>Myth 3: DSCI is a one-size-fits-all solution</strong> DSCI is a flexible field, but it’s not a universal fix for all problems. Each project requires a customized approach based on the specific context, objectives, data, and audience, and they vary depending on the data type and the problem at hand.</p> <p>Let’s remember that DSCI is a dynamic and multifaceted field that transcends these myths. By debunking these misconceptions, we can gain a better understanding of the true essence of DSCI and continue exploring its boundless possibilities.</p> <p>Feel free to share your thoughts and experiences regarding these myths or any other misconceptions you’ve encountered in the realm of DSCI!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data-sci"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hey everyone!]]></summary></entry></feed>